[
{
  "question": "A rigid 800L container holds a 30kg sample of CO2 at 280K. The CO2 is slowly heated to 400K. Calculate the pressure in the container both before and after being heated up. Assume that the CO2 is behaving like an ideal gas.",
  "answer": {
      "code": """
import numpy as np

V = 800 * 0.001 # Volume (m^3)
m = 30 # mass (kg)
T1 = 280 # initial temperature (K)
T2 = 400 # final temperature (K)
R = 188.92 # specific gas constant of CO2 (J/kg*K)

#The ideal gas equation is PV = mRT
P1 = (m * R * T1) / V # initial pressure (Pa)
P2 = (m * R * T2) / V # final pressure (Pa)

print("The pressure in the container before being heated up is ", P1, " pascals,\ and the pressure in the container after being heated up is ", P2, " pascals.")
      """,
      "explanation": "This code calculates the change in pressure using the ideal gas equation which relates the pressure, volume, and temperature of an ideal gas. It uses the formula PV = mRT, where 'P' is the pressure of the gas, 'V' is the volume of the container holding the gas, 'm' is the mass of the gas, 'R' is the gas constant of the gas, and 'T' is the temperature of the gas."
      "references": [
          "Professor Zaidi's lecture slides"
      ]
  }
},
{
  "question": "At a given point on the wing of a Boeing 727, the pressure and temperature of the air are 2.4 x 10^4 N/m^2 and 210K, respectively. What is the density of the air at this point?",
  "answer": {
      "code": """
import numpy as np

R = 287 # specific gas constant of air (J/kg*K)
P = 24000 # pressure of the air (Pa)
T = 210 # temperature (K)

# Use the ideal gas equation
rho = P / (R*T)

print("The density of the air is ", rho, " pascals.")
      """,
      "explanation": "This code calculates the density using an alternate form of the ideal gas equations, P = rho * RT, where P is the pressure of the gas, rho is the density of the gas, R is the gas constant of the gas, and T is the temperature of the gas."
      "references": [
          "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 98, problem 1.1a"
      ]
  }
},
{
  "question": "A U-tube mercury manometer is used to measure the pressure at a point on the wing of a wind-tunnel model. One side of the manometer is connected to the model, and the other side is open to the atmosphere. Atmospheric pressure and the density of the mercury are 1.01 x 10^5 N/m^2 and 1.36 x 10^4 kg/m^3, respectively. When the displacement of the two columns of mercury is 20 cm, with the high column on the model side, what is the pressure on the wing?",
  "answer": {
      "code": """
import numpy as np

Patm = 101000 # Pressure of the atmosphere (Pa)
rhol = 13600 # Density of the mercury (kg/m^3)
h = 0.2 # Height difference of the mercury in the two tubes (m)
g = 9.8 # gravitational acceleration constant (m/s^2)

# The pressure in a tube can be calculated by adding the pressure at the opening of the tube with the pressure exerted by the fluid above the depth of interest.
# The pressure at a specific depth is the same in both tubes. The pressure in the tube on the model side is Pm + rhol * gh, where Pm is the pressure on the wing.
# The pressure in the tube on the side open to the atmosphere is Patm + rhoa * gh, where rhoa is the density of air. Since the density of air is very small, the rhoa * gh term can be considered negligible.
# Setting the two equations equal to each other and rearranging some terms, we get that Pm = Patm - rhol * gh.

Pm = Patm - rhol * g * h

print("The pressure on the wing is ", Pm, " pascals.")
      """,
      "references": [
          "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 100, problem 1.11"
      ]
  }
},
{
  "question": "Consider the flow properties a point in the flow where the temperature is 320K and the velocity is 1000 m/s. Calculate the Mach number at this point",
  "answer": {
      "code": """
import numpy as np

gamma = 1.4 # specific heat ratio of air
R = 287 # specific gas constant of air (J/kg*K)
T = 320 # temperature (K)
V = 1000 # velocity of the gas (m/s)

# The Mach number can be calculated as V/a, where 'V' is velocity and 'a' is the speed of sound.
# a can be calculated as sqrt(gamma * RT). Putting the two equations together, we get M = V/sqrt(gamma * RT)
M = V / np.sqrt(gamma * R * T)

print("The Mach number at this point is ", M)
      """,
      "explanation": "This code calculates the Mach number using the Mach number equation and the equation for the speed of sound, M = V/sqrt(gamma * RT), where M is the Mach number, V is the velocity in m/s, gamma is the specific heat ratio, and T is the temperature in K."
      "references": [
          "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 560, example 8.2"
      ]
  }
},
{
  "question": "Consider a long tube with a length of 300m. The tube is filled with helium, a monatomic gas, at a temperature of 320K. A sound wave is generated at one end of the tube. How long will it take for the wave to reach the other end?",
  "answer": {
      "code": """
import numpy as np

d = 300 # distance (m)
gamma = 1.67 # specific heat ratio of monatomic gases
R = 2078.5 # specific gas constant of helium (J/kg*K)
T = 320 # temperature (K)

# The distance travelled by an object can be calculated with d = vt, where d is the distance, v is the speed of the object, and t is time
# The velocity of sound is given by sqrt(gamma * RT). Combining these two formulas and rearranging some terms, we get that t = d/sqrt(gamma * RT)
t = d / np.sqrt(gamma * R * T)

print("It would take ", t, " seconds for the sound wave to reach the end of the tube.")
      """
      "explanation": "This code calculates the time it takes for sound to travel by using a combination of the distance and speed of sound formulas, t = d/sqrt(gamma * RT), where d is distance, gamma is the specific heat ratio, R is the specific gas constant, and T is the temperature."
      "references": [
          "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 564, example 8.6"
      ]
  }
},
{
  "question": "Consider a flow along a streamline with a velocity of 50 m/s, a density of 1.23 kg/m^3, and a pressure of 1.01 x 10^5 N/m^2. The pressure at a point downstream the streamline is decreased to 0.9 x 10^5 N/m^2. Assuming that the flow is incompressible, what is the velocity at this point?",
  "answer": {
      "code": """
import numpy as np

v1 = 50 # upstream velocity (m/s)
p1 = 101000 # upstream pressure (Pa)
rho = 1.23 # density (kg/m^3)
p2 = 90000 # downstream pressure (Pa)

# Use Bernoulli's equation, p1 + 0.5 * rho * v1^2 = p2 + 0.5 * rho * v2^2 => v2 = sqrt(2(p1 - p2)/rho + v1^2)
v2 = np.sqrt((2*(p1 - p2) / rho) + v1**2)

print("The velocity downstream is ", v2, " m/s.")
      """
      "explanation": "This code calculates the downstream velocity using Bernoulli's equation, p1 + 0.5*rho*v1^2 = p2 + 0.5*rho*v2^2, where p1 and p2 are the upstream and downstream pressures, v1 and v2 are the upstream and downstream velocities, and rho is the density of the fluid."
      "references": [
          "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 210, example 3.1"
      ]
  }
},
{
  "question": "Consider the gas in the resevoir of a supersonic wind tunnel. The pressure and temperature of the air in the resevoir are 20 atm and 300K respectively. The air in the resevoir isentropically expands through the wind tunnel duct until it reaches a point where the pressure of the air is 1 atm. Calculate the temperature at this point.",
  "answer": {
      "code": """
import numpy as np

T1 = 300 # initial temperature (K)
p1 = 20 # initial pressure (atm)
p2 = 1 # final pressure (atm)
gamma = 1.4 # specific heat ratio of air

# Use the isentropic relations for pressure and temperature, (p2/p1) = (T2/T1)^(gamma/(gamma-1)) => T2 = T1(p2/p1)^((gamma-1)/gamma)
T2 = T1 * (p2/p1)**((gamma-1)/gamma)

print("The temperature of the air is ", T2, "K.");
      """
      "explanation": "This code calculates temperature using the isentropic relations, (p2/p1) = (T2/T1)^(gamma/(gamma-1)) => T2 = T1(p2/p1)^((gamma-1)/gamma), where p1 and p2 is the pressure at state 1 and state 2 respectively, T1 and T2 is the temperature at state 1 and state 2 respectively, and gamma is the specific heat ratio."
      "references": [
          "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 529, example 7.5a"
      ]

  }
},
{
  "question": "A rigid 90L container holding 20kg of CO2 is heated from 300K to 400K. What is the work done by the gas during this process?",
  "answer": "The work done by a gas can be found with the integration of pdV between state one and state two, where p is the pressure of the gas, and dV is the change in volume. Because the container is rigid, there is no change in volume, meaning the gas did not do any work."
},
{
  "question": "Explain the differences between non-ideal gases,, ideal gases, semi-perfect gases, and perfect gases.",
  "answer": "The properties of non-ideal gases , such as pressure, temperature, and volume, can't be related using the ideal gas equation and must be determined empirically. Meanwhile, the ideal gas equation can be used for determining the relationships between the properties of an ideal gas. Semi-perfect gases and perfect gases are both subsets of ideal gases, where semi-perfect gases have heat capacities that vary depending on temperature, while perfect gases have heat capacities that are independent of the temperature of the gas."
},
{
  "question": "What exactly is a shock wave, and how do flow properties change across it?",
  "answer": "A shock wave is a very small region of supersonic flow where flow properties change by a large amount near instantaneously. Across a shock wave, the Mach number decreases, the stagnation pressure decreases, the entropy, density, static pressure, and static temperature increase, and the stagnation enthalpy and stagnation temperature remain constant."
  "references:" [
      "https://www.grc.nasa.gov/www/k-12/airplane/oblique.html#:~:text=The%20change%20in%20flow%20properties,are%20generated%20in%20the%20flow"
  ]
},
{
  "question": "What do all the lines on an expansion fan diagram mean?", # I'm not sure if this is a dumb question, but it was one I had and the internet didn't do a good job explaining it, so I figured that I should include it
  "answer": "The lines on a Prandtl-Meyer expansion fan are meant to be a representation of an infinite number of Mach waves, each changing the flow angle and flow velocity by a small and continuous amount."
  "references:" [
      "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, Chapter 9.6"
  ]
},
{
  "question": "Bernoulli's principle doesn't make any sense. Why doesn't increasing inlet pressure increase the velocity of the fluid at the inlet?",
  "answer": "It may help to think of Bernoulli's principle in terms of F = ma. Fluid flowing from a high pressure region to a low pressure region will accelerate due to the net force from the difference in pressure along the direction of the flow. For example, increasing the inlet pressure will cause the fluid to accelerate, resulting in a higher outlet velocity where the pressure is lower."
  "references": [
      "https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/fluids/fluid-dynamics/a/what-is-bernoullis-equation"
  ]
},
{
  "question": "What are pitot-static tubes and how do they work?",
  "answer": "Pitot-static tubes are measurement devices that measure both the stagnation pressure and static pressure in order to determine the velocity of a fluid. A probe facing the direction of the fluid flow isentropically brings the flow to rest, allowing for the measurement of the stagnation pressure, which is equal to the static pressure + the dynamic pressure. Another probe angled 90 degrees away from the flow direction measures the static pressure. These measurements can then be used to find the dynamic pressure, which is described as 1/2 * density * velocity of the flow^2. This can then be used to find the velocity of the flow."
},
{
  "question": "On T-s diagrams, why do constant volume lines have larger slopes than consstant pressure lines?",
  "answer": "To find the slope of a constant volume line, we can use the Tds equation Tds = du + pdv. If volume is constant, then this term is reduced to Tds = du, where du = C_v * dT. Rearranging some terms, we get that dT/ds = T/C_v. A similar process can be done using the equation Tds = dh - vdp for constant pressure lines, where dh = C_p * dT and dp = 0. This results in the equation dT/ds = T/C_p. Since the constant pressure specific heat capacity (C_p) is larger than the constant volume specific heat capacity (C_v), the constant volume line has a greater slope than the constant pressure line on a T-s diagram."
},
{
  "question": "What causes oblique shocks to form, and why do they form at all?",
  "answer": "An oblique shock forms when a fluid traveling at supersonic speeds is interrupted by a wedge in the flow. Because the fluid is flowing at a speed greater than the speed of information, the flow direction and properties upstream the wedge does not change. When the flow meets the wedge, it can't travel through the wedge and will instead abruptly change direction at an angle known as the wave angle, creating an oblique shock."
  "references": [
      "Yunus A. Çengel, Michael A. Boles, Mehmet Kanoğlu (2023) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw Hill, Chapter 18-5"
  ]
},
{
  "question": "Why do fluid properties still change throughout steady flow? I thought steady flow was defined as no change over time?"
  "answer": "Steady flow is defined as flow where all points of the flow remain constant in respects to time. However, the flow properties are only constant at one point in space. As soon as the fluid moves from one point in the flow to another, its properties can change. The flow is still considered steady as long as its properties at each point in space remain constant over time."
},
]